<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.tabularisdb.Tabularis</id>

  <name>Tabularis</name>
  <summary>Open-source database client with AI, notebooks, and plugins</summary>

  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>Apache-2.0</project_license>

  <developer id="dev.tabularis">
    <name>Tabularis</name>
  </developer>

  <description>
    <p>
      Tabularis is a free, open-source desktop database client for PostgreSQL,
      MySQL/MariaDB, and SQLite. Built with Rust (Tauri v2) and React, it is
      fast, lightweight, and designed for everyday SQL work.
    </p>
    <p>Key features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>SQL Notebooks: combine SQL and Markdown cells with inline charts, cross-cell variables, parameters, and export to HTML/CSV/JSON.</li>
      <li>AI-powered SQL assistant: generate SQL from natural language, explain queries, and get optimization suggestions. Works with OpenAI, Claude, Ollama (local), OpenRouter, and any OpenAI-compatible API.</li>
      <li>Built-in MCP server for AI agent integration with Claude Desktop, Claude Code, Cursor, and Windsurf.</li>
      <li>Visual query builder with drag-and-drop JOINs, filters, aggregates, and real-time SQL generation.</li>
      <li>Plugin system to add any database driver (DuckDB, ClickHouse, MongoDB, and more) using JSON-RPC plugins in any language.</li>
      <li>Monaco-based SQL editor with smart autocomplete, a high-performance virtualized data grid with inline editing, ER diagram visualization, SSH tunneling, system keychain credential storage, split view, SQL dump/import, 10+ themes, and multi-language support.</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.tabularisdb.Tabularis.desktop</launchable>

  <url type="homepage">https://tabularis.dev</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/TabularisDB/tabularis/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/TabularisDB/tabularis</url>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://tabularis.dev/img/overview.png</image>
      <caption>Overview of the Tabularis workspace</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://tabularis.dev/img/tabularis-split-view.png</image>
      <caption>Split view for working on multiple queries side by side</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://tabularis.dev/img/tabularis-query-history-sidebar.png</image>
      <caption>Query history sidebar</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://tabularis.dev/img/tabularis-favorites-sidebar.png</image>
      <caption>Favorites sidebar for quick access to saved queries</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#020617</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#e2e8f0</color>
  </branding>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.13.1" date="2026-06-16" />
  </releases>
</component>
